A Guide to the Lynchburg (Va.) Deeds, 1805-1936 (bulk 1817-1906)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lynchburg (Va.) Deeds, 1805-1936 (bulk 1817-1906)
The Library of Virginia
19.8 cubic feet (44 boxes); 18 volumes
Lynchburg (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Lynchburg County (Va.) Bills of Sale and Deeds,1807-1865, involving enslaved and free Black and Multiracial individuals are digitized and available through Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from the city of Lynchburg.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Bills of sale are written agreements which convey title of property, including enslaved people, from seller to buyer. Under the system of chattel slavery, laws permitted enslavers to treat enslaved people as personal possessions in the same manner as livestock, farm equipment, or household items. Enslaved people could be bought or sold without regard to their personal relationships or free will. Bills of sale record the name of the seller, the names of enslaved people being sold and their price, and the name of the buyer. Given that they involved a property transaction, bills of sale were commonly recorded and filed with deeds in the local court. However, there was no official requirement that the transfer of an enslaved person be recorded unless necessary for legal purposes such as a court case or an estate settlement. Enslaved people could also be transferred through a deed of gift, there was no money transaction involved in this case, which distinguishes this record from a bill of sale. Enslavers and their family members often transferred enslaved people between themselves in this manner.
Deeds are written agreements which convey title of property, such as an enslaved person, from one individual to another. These include the voluntary transfer of enslaved people between family members with no financial transaction involved. Deeds include the names of the grantors, grantees, and enslaved people. Clerks proved, acknowledged, and recorded deeds in the local court.
Locality History: Lynchburg, in Campbell County, was named for John Lynch, the owner of the original town site. It was established in 1786, was incorporated as a town in 1805, and became a city in 1852. Parts of Campbell and Bedford counties were annexed to the city in 1976.
Scope and Content
Lynchburg (Va.) Deeds, 1805-1936 (bulk 1817-1906) consist of deeds of bargain and sale, deeds of gift, mortgages, bills of sale, and deeds of trust. Included are two boxes of processed and indexed material consisting of bills of sale and deeds,1807-1865, involving free and enslaved Black individuals.
Deeds of bargain and sale are the most recorded deed in which one individual sells property, usually land, but occasionally personal property, to another individual. Such deeds show the names of the grantor and grantee, the residence of both parties, a description of what is being sold, the consideration (or price), the location of the tract of land, the tract's boundaries, and any limitations on the property being sold. The deed was signed by the grantor, and possibly his wife or anyone else having a claim to the property, and by at least two witnesses. Appended to the deed may be a memorandum of livery of seisin, stating that the property has changed hands and that peaceful possession has taken place.
Deeds of gift are often found transferring property, either real or personal including enslaved people, from one individual to another "for love and affection." The degree of kinship, if any, between the grantor and grantee is sometimes stated. Information recorded included name(s) of the grantor(s), grantee(s), and enslaved people. Deeds of gift were proved and recorded in the local court.
Mortgages and deeds of trust were deeds where one party is indebted to another and transfers or mortgages property to a third party to secure the debt.
Bills of sale are written agreements which convey title of property, such as an enslaved person, from seller to buyer. Bills of sale record the name of the seller, the names of enslaved persons being sold and their price, and the name of the buyer. Given that they involved a property transaction, bills of sale were commonly recorded and filed with deeds in the local court.
Also includes bound volumes of general indexes to loose deeds, 1805-1936.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Deeds and bills of sale,1807-1865, involving free and enslaved people, arranged chronologically
Series II: Deeds and records related to, 1805-1936, arranged chronologically
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: Lynchburg (Va.) Free and Enslaved Records, 1834-1837, undated
Records related to free and enslaved people of Lynchburg (Va.) and other localities are available through the Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website.
Deed Books and Indices to Deeds for Lynchburg can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Additional Lynchburg Land Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Deeds and Bills of Sale, relating to free and enslaved Black and multiracial persons, 1807-1865, .45 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  arranged chronologically.
  - Deeds, 1807-1843
  - Deeds and Unrecorded Deeds, 1844-1865
- Deeds and records relating to, 1805-1936, 18.9 cubic feet (42 boxes); 18 volumes
  arranged chronologically
  - Deeds, 1805-1929
    - Deeds 1805
    - Deeds 1817
    - Deeds 1818
    - Deeds 1819-1821
    - Deeds 1821-1824
    - Deeds 1825-1827
    - Deeds 1828-1831
    - Deeds 1832-1833
    - Deeds 1834-1836
    - Deeds 1837-1839
    - Deeds 1840-1842
    - Deeds 1843-1845
    - Deeds 1846 - 1848
    - Deeds 1849-1851
    - Deeds 1852-1854
    - Deeds 1855-1857
    - Deeds 1858-1860
    - Deeds 1861-1869
    - Deeds 1870-1874
    - Deeds 1875-1876
    - Deeds 1877-1879
    - Deeds 1879-1881
    - Deeds 1881-1882
    - Deeds 1883
    - Deeds 1884
    - Deeds 1885
    - Deeds 1886
    - Deeds 1887
    - Deeds 1888-1889
    - Deeds 1890
    - Deeds 1891
    - Deeds 1892
    - Deeds 1893
    - Deeds 1894
    - Deeds 1895
    - Deeds 1896
    - Deeds 1897
    - Deeds 1898
    - Deeds 1899
    - Deeds 1900
    - Deeds 1901-1906, 1929
  - General Indexes, 1805-1936
    - General Index to Deeds 1805-1841
    - General Index to Deeds 1841-1876
    - General Index to Deeds 1876-1888
    - General Index to Deeds 1888
    - General Index to Deeds 1894
    - General Index to Deeds 1899
    - General Index to Deeds 1902
    - General Index to Deeds 1907
    - General Index to Deeds 1910-1913
    - General Index to Deeds 1913
    - General Index to Deeds 1916-1919
    - General Index to Deeds 1920-1922
    - General Index to Deeds 1922
    - General Index to Deeds 1925
    - General Index to Deeds 1927
    - General Index to Deeds 1930
    - General Index to Deeds 1932
    - General Index to Deeds 1936